# PEDRO HERRUZO SÁNCHEZ O SAN JOSÉ, CALIFORNIA

Data Scientist / Research Fellow at IARAI

@ pherrusa7@gmail.com

% pherrusa7.github.io

in linkedin.com/in/pherrusa7

github.com/pherrusa7

**\** +1(669)307-0031

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Associate Pre-doctoral Research Fellow Institute of Advanced Research in Artificial Intelligence - IARAI

Feb 2020 - Present · +1 yrs

**♀** Vienna, Austria / remote

Deep Learning for Spatio-Temporal Data: Video Prediction, and Datasets and Metrics design. Data Fusion (Multimodal & Multiresolution), Transfer / Few-Shot Learning, and Extreme Events. Co-organizer of:

- The Weather4cast competition @IEEE Big Data Cup 2021
- The Traffic4cast competition @NeurIPS 2020 and 2021
- 1st Workshop on Complex Data Challenges in Earth Observation @CIKM 2021

## Machine Learning Consultant & Data Scientist SEAT. S.A.

♥ Barcelona, Spain

Leading Machine Learning for future urban mobility:

- Mobility Advisor (presented in MWC 19 together with IBM).
- Socially Responsible Navigation (presented in SCEWC 18 together with Waze and the city council of Barcelona).

### **Graduate Research Fellowship** University of Barcelona - CVUB group

Parcelona, Spain

Explainable deep learning for the automatic recognition of lifestyle patterns (time spent eating, socializing, and seated) from wearable cameras.

#### **BI** Consultant

#### Indra Sistemas, S.A.

May 2014 - Feb 2016 · 1 yr 10 mos ♥ Barcelona, Spain

Exploitation of Data Warehouse Commercial Segurcaixa, Vidacaixa.

## HONORS AWARDS

NeurlPS2019 Workshop: Outstanding Contribution

Traffic4cast competition by the Institute of Advanced Research in Artificial Intelligence (IARAI) and HERE Technologies.

Climate Change Challenge 2019: 3th position

Organized by the University of Barcelona, ISGlobal, and Ajuntament de Barcelona: Modeling the weather in the city of Barcelona.

Big Data & Al Congress Barcelona 2018: Best Master Thesis We analyzed first-person stories automatically by means of egocentric pictures acquired with wearable cameras using AI.

DKV Seguros Health4Good 2016: Ideas Contest for Startups Second prize: an App that can create nutrition diaries automatically from only pictures, also proposing healthy eating habits.

### **EDUCATION**

#### Ph.D. in Artificial Intelligence Polytechnic University of Catalonia

**2018 - 2023** 

**♀** Barcelona, Spain

Deep learning for Spatio-temporal data with applications to mobility and weather forecasting

Deep Learning Indaba 2019 **Kenyatta University - Summer School** 

Nairobi, Kenya

M.Sc. in Fundamental Principles of Data Science

**University of Barcelona** 

Double B.Sc. in Computer Engineering and Mathematics

**University of Barcelona** 

**University of Groningen - Erasmus** 

Feb 2016 - Jul 2016 • Groningen, Netherlands

B.BA. in Business Administration and Management

**University of Barcelona** 

I finished a 3 years degree in only 2

### **TEACHING**

**Teaching Assistant** Pompeu Fabra University

Intro to Programming: 1st-year / Python.

**University of Barcelona** 

- Data Structures: 1st-year / C++.
- Operating systems I: 2nd-year / C.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- Gruca, Aeksandra et al. (2021). "CDCEO 21 First Workshop on Complex Data Challenges in Earth Observation". In: 30th ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM 21). DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3459637.3482044.
- Kopp, Michael et al. (2021). "Traffic4cast at NeurIPS 2020 yet more on the unreasonable effectiveness of gridded geo-spatial processes". In: NeurIPS 2020 Competition and Demonstration Track, Proceedings of Machine Learning Research 133. Ed. by Hugo Jair Escalante and Katja Hofmann, pp. 325-343. URL: https://proceedings.mlr. press/v133/kopp21a.html.
- Herruzo, Pedro and Josep L. Larriba-Pey (2020). "Recurrent Autoencoder with Skip Connections and Exogenous Variables for Traffic Forecasting". In: NeurIPS 2019 Competition and Demonstration Track, Proceedings of Machine Learning Research 123. Ed. by Hugo Jair Escalante and Raia Hadsell, pp. 47-55. URL: http://proceedings. mlr.press/v123/herruzo20a.html.
- Kreil, David P et al. (2020). "The surprising efficiency of framing geospatial time series forecasting as a video prediction task - Insights from the IARAI t4c Competition at NeurIPS 2019". In: NeurIPS 2019 Competition and Demonstration Track, Proceedings of Machine Learning Research 123. Ed. by Hugo Jair Escalante and Raia Hadsell, pp. 232-241. URL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v123/kreil20a.html.
- Herruzo, Pedro et al. (2019). "Towards Objective Description of Eating, Socializing and Sedentary Lifestyle Patterns in Egocentric Images". In: Workshop on Applications of Egocentric Vision (EgoApp'19), British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC) 2019. DOI: DOI: https: //dx.doi.org/10.5244/C.33.348.
- (2017). "Analyzing First-Person Stories Based on Socializing, Eating and Sedentary Patterns". In: Lecture Notes in Computer Science 10590, pp. 109-119. URL: https://arxiv.org/pdf/1707.07863.
- Herruzo, P., M. Bolaños, and P. Radeva (2016). "Can a CNN recognize Catalan diet?" In: AIP Conference Proceedings 1773, p. 020002. URL: https://aip.scitation.org/doi/abs/10.1063/1.4964956.

## SELECTED TALKS

The Weather4cast competition @IEEE Big Data Cup 2021. July 2021 · Virtual · ICML: Weather4cast Challenge @IARAI.



Recurrent Autoencoder for Traffic Forecasting

Dec 2019 · Vancouver, Canada · NeurIPS: Traffic4cast Challenge.



Keeping Society Moving In A Connected World

Feb 2019 · BCN · 4YFN / MWC w. Avichai Bakst @Waze.



You 4 Socially Responsible Navigation

Nov 2018 · BCN · SCEWC w. Luca de Meo (CEO @SEAT, S.A.).



Big Data Talent Awards for the best master thesis

Nov 2018 · Big Data & Al Congress Barcelona Congress.

#### **ABOUT ME**

"I am a data scientist, with a strong technical background in machine learning, math and programming, and the experience to bring these fields together to create useful real-life applications. Throughout my life, I have had the opportunity to develop proficient public **speaking**, teamwork, time management, and leadership skills. I take pleasure in overcoming challenges and being creative, dedicated, and proactive. I enjoy human relations and like getting involved in and helping to manage social activities."

### **STRENGTHS**

Communication Management		
Social Skills Strategy		
Machine Learning Computer Vision		
Explainable AI Transformers		
Graph Neural Networks		
Recurrent Neural Networks Datasets		
Metrics Spatio-Temporal Data		
Weather Predictions		
Urban Traffic Predictions		
Caffe, Keras, PyTorch, TensorFlow		
C C++ C# git Java Linux		
Matlab Python R SQL		
CSS   HTML   Javascript		

# LANGUAGES

Catalan	••••
English	••••
Spanish	••••

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>https://youtu.be/1DRZaiUlfUE

<sup>2</sup>https://youtu.be/8y\_Pwiy9C5M?t=2681

<sup>3</sup>https://youtu.be/qERNVybd1Z8?t=628

<sup>4</sup>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QoOmbgm5sHA

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>5</sup>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cqcCK3YHDVk&t=4m13s